Yeah, this is Gotham. So, general
insurance can be a very daunting
business to understand at first. All
right. And if I would tell you the
general insurance and banking uh the
business models are pretty similar. So,
it would sound very weird, right? So, in
this video, let me simplify all this for
you. Okay? Uh so if you're a young or an
experienced investor or you're an
aspiring equity analyst or you're a
strategy consultant okay then uh in this
video I would help you understand how
you can go about and do fundamental
analysis of a general insurer okay so
please allow me 30 minutes of your time
all right because I'm going to go into a
lot of detail and by the end of it you
would really appreciate the business
model for general insurer and you would
be able to do fundamental analysis of an
insurance company on your own.
>> So uh see uh in one of his shareholder
letters Warren Buffett has spoken about
how he spots a great business. So what
he has gone on to say is a truly great
business must have an enduring moat
meaning castle that protects excellent
returns on capital. Okay. But he says in
a capitalist society okay comes will
repeatedly assault any business any
business castle that is earning high
returns on capital. Okay. He also goes
on to say there is no one formula in
finance that you can use to measure
business modes. Okay. But the
all-encompassing metric that comes
closest is return on capital or roe for
financial services. So a business okay
which is able to demonstrate let's say a
high ROIC or high RO high ROE in the
case of financial services. If a
business, if a financial services
business is able to deliver a high ROE
for a prolonged period of time, okay,
then it is able to do so because it has
more
factors.
Okay, let's move forward.
Okay. So first understand the let's
understand the drivers of ROE
pat divided by equity per rupee of
dollar of equity what is the profit that
you are making that is your roe
equity
or roe can be expanded into you know
broken up into two parameters. One is
your ROA return on assets which is
essentially bad by assets or the per
rupee of assets how much profit you are
making. Okay. And then leverage is
assets divide by equity per rupee of
equity assets you have you have on your
balance sheet. Okay. So that's that's
the simple and of course
theor
right financial services business.
So why is important to first place? If
you see uh the snippet that I have here,
long-term stock compounding for
financial institutions, okay, they
follow book value per share compounding
which in turn depends upon the company's
ability to deliver high RO over the long
term. Okay. Again,
is very important
over long period of time. Okay.
Which is fine because of something like
more often than not the business a good
business will have a handsome ro over
long period of time. Okay. when I say
handsome good is let's say cost of
equity 10 11% to ro should be more than
10 11% should be 14 15% okay over
extended periods of time okay so that's
a a very like rough uh yard stick that
you can use okay of course the higher
the RO the better let's move forward
>> all right
>> so before we understanding
general insurance or banks or other
financial services
that is what specifically we need look
and analyze in a general insurer in a
bank and other financial institutions.
First let's try to understand the
business model of a general insurer and
a bank. Okay. And I have a very weird
headline. It says business model of
general insurers is largely the same as
banks. Okay. So basically
a general insurer makes money largely
the same way as a bank. And it's very
interesting guys. Please just follow
along uh for some time. Okay. You'll
love it. Okay.
Let's understand a business model for a
bank
model.
So we as customers okay we deposit our
saving our salary what have you uh with
a bank. Okay. And banks they give us a
small interest uh you know uh on on the
on our deposits. So let's say that
interest is 4%. Okay. And then bank will
give the same money as loan to a
different customer. Okay. So let's say
the bank makes 8% interest income on
that money okay which it has given out
as a loan to the differential
bank made a net interest income of 4%
business model bank okay business model
interest income you net out this 4%
which is cost of fund or interest income
expense for a bank and then the bank is
left with 4% as net interest income okay
or in that 4%
You know you of course bank also makes
money through fee lot of fee income say
bank makes money okay because you can do
so many transactions when you have a net
banking you can do so many transactions
and then you net out operating expense
provision tax so let's say after adding
this and netting all of this out the
bank
is left with 2%.
2% is your ROA return on assets.
Let's say if a bank has given out a loan
of rupees 100 okay then it is making 2
rupees as return that is what ROI of 2%
means okay okay India with large banks
say we'll see in subsequent HDFC ICICI
kak these are making ROA of 2% and
higher I think higher than 2% we'll see
that in the next slide okay all Right.
Okay. All right. This is how business
this is the business model of a bank.
Okay. Now, uh
dep we we as customers deposit with the
bank. We can take out any point in time.
That's our money. That's the money bank
uh holds but bank doesn't own that
money. Deposit bank uh holds but it
doesn't own that money. Okay, it will
give us an interest so long as we we
have a deposit park in the bank deposit
case for a bank in case let's try to
understand there is something called
float float if you understand the
concept of float trust me you learned
you'll love this business and you you
know you you'll be able to analyze any
insurer you'll be able to pick good
insurers for your investments as well
Okay, lot of uh people a lot of good
investors in the world they have made a
fortune by picking by investing in in
goods insurance. Anyway, so let's
understand float. Okay,
insurers they collect premiums
from people like us. Okay, uh but often
don't pay a lot of claims until a later
point in time, sometimes years later.
During that time, they invest the
remaining premium money. remaining
premium money called float to earn
interest income. Okay, float is the
money insurers hold but don't own.
Please
you'll get an appreciation of the
business model of a general insurer.
Okay. So let's say uh IC Lombard it gets
125 rupees as premium in a given year.
Okay. Of the 125 rupees that it receives
as premium let's say it sets aside 20
rupees reserve 20 rupees okay side okay
you reserve
and then 5 rupees it pays as premium to
a general to general insurance
corporation of India. Okay. So it's left
with 100 rupees 5 rupees this is set
aside for extreme risky events if they
happen at some point in the future then
general insurance corporation of India
GIC will come to the rescue okay or 20
rupees set aside okay that is also set
aside for let's say if in certain years
there are more claim payments that they
need to make than they had originally
thought of this 20 is set aside for any
for
okay to 20 rupees of reserve
this is added to something which is
called
float
okay float is nothing but investment
assets okay yeah this is not uh the pesa
of insurers this is the money they hold
but they don't own okay
then so any which way in See ICC Lombard
is left with 100 rupees of this 100
rupees. Okay. Let's say they pay 70 as
claim payments in that year. Okay. Which
claim payments and then let's say they
pay 28 rupees in expenses. Expenses
operational expenses they pay as
expenses. Okay. So they are left with
rupees 2. Okay. This rupees 2
is called underwriting profit.
Okay. Okay,
20 rupees of reserve plus this 2 rupees.
Okay, all this in a way gets added to
float.
Okay, and this process repeats every
year. Okay. All right. So, but if you
think of float key, so this repeats
every year. So, the float eventually
becomes a very big amount. Okay. And
they invest that money and earn an
interest income on that money. Okay.
business
basically definition. Okay, hopefully
you kind of understood.
Okay, see you if you see if you try to
draw parallels between how a bank makes
money and how a general insurer makes
money. Okay, so let's say investment
deal by investing float. Okay, in uh by
investing float let's say insurer makes
8%. Okay, then there is something called
cost of float. your cost of funds for an
insurer that we'll understand in a bit
in the subsequent slide. Okay, let's say
cost of float let's say cost of float
I'm just making it up 3%. Okay, then
return on float is or return on assets
is 5%. I know.
All right.
If you try to draw parall, what it means
is insurer, okay, raises money, okay, at
a certain cost, which we'll understand
in a bit, okay? It raises money in the
form of premiums at a certain cost,
okay, and invests that money and on that
money it earns a earns an interest. The
differential between the investment
yield the interest income
and the cost at which it raised that
money that surplus premium is your
return on assets.
All right to similarity business model
okay but of course the way they go about
making this return on assets return on
float is of course different. Okay. So
hope you kind of get the uh get the
understand the business model
cost of so now let's understand cost of
float. Okay in in a in the subsequent
slide. Let's move forward.
If you're a budding investor interested
in learning thorough fundamental
analysis and valuation or if you're an
aspiring equity research analyst,
financial analyst or a consultant who's
interested in learning these skills to
get into such roles, okay, then I have a
program suited to your needs. Okay, in
my equity research and valuation
learning program, I cover quality and
well search content. I cover diverse
industry business models. Okay, and this
is a and I have a growing community.
Okay. So, and I also have the list of
topics which I cover which on this slide
which will help you become a
well-rounded or thorough analyst. All
right. So, get in touch if you
interested in learning more details
about this program. All right. Thank
you. Now, uh with that now we have a
good sense of business model for general
insurer. Yeah. Let's see what is it that
we need to analyze when we do
fundamental analysis of a general
insurer
to fundamentally analyze an insurer.
Okay. So the first two key things as you
saw versus ROA
and the second is leverage combination
of RO and leverage they drive ROE for a
insurer. Okay. Just we saw RO
differential between investment yield
and cost of float. Cost of fund
cost of import.
It's almost constant. It's fixed. Okay.
That moves up and down. Okay. That's
a well-run general insurer. A well
general insurer will have very low cost
of float, low cost of funds for a
prolonged period of time. There will be
less variability in its cost of float
and a well insurer will try to keep its
cost of float to a bare minimum level
over a period of time.
It will drive higher RO and high
cost of
the cost of
you need underwriting loss divided by
float. Okay to let me uh move over to
let me show you cost of float. Okay.
See cost of float I I'm just sharing a
LinkedIn post. Uh I hope it's visible.
Yeah. All right. So in this LinkedIn
post I have uh the combined ratios of
these insurers listed here. Okay.
Combined ratio. Combined ratio.
Combined ratio of a general insurer is
simple way to measure how profitable the
insurer is from its core business. Okay.
So let's say example let's say net
premium collected net premium collected
claim payments 70
expenses is 30. Okay
as claim and as expenses.
Okay.
to if that is the case then combined
ratio is 100
no profit no loss from underwriting
okay or combined ratio less than 100
okay that means the insurer is making a
profit from underwriting if the combined
ratio is greater than 100 that means
insurer is making an underwriting loss
okay to 100 ratios is the insurer is
making an underwriting loss so you see
net India insurance is making huge
underwriting losses
Go Digit is making some underwriting
losses. IC Lombard is making small
underwriting losses as well. Star Health
made an underwriting profit in the first
two years and now it's only slightly at
a loss.
No, nothing like that. No, far from the
truth.
As I said,
Okay.
Okay. Even though
103%
fruit
they set 20 aside
they give 70 as claim plus they give 33
as expenses 103
Okay. All right. So this is the logic.
So even though if
even though an insurer
even though insurer is making small
underwriting losses doesn't mean it's a
bad insurer. With that understanding let
me
underwriting cost of fruit. Okay.
So I have the star health investor
presentation open. So you see star
health as you saw combined ratio
95 97 and now 101. Okay. So on paper
they seem to be doing a really good job
at keeping their combined ratios under
control. So now now
right see to calculate cost of
you need something called underwriting
profits.
Okay.
loss 378 lowus 378 I'm writing loss
divided by float float
okay float
float is float is how to check for float
investment asset
investment assets
mentioned
total investment assets this is nothing
but flow
okay to 1789 8C cr worth of floaty year
investment assets they have been able to
accumulate since the time they've
started their business this is the float
they have accumulated over time 17898 CR
at CR they have accumulated as float
float 3 - 378
minus 178998
this would be your cost of float the
cost of float
Cost of float is 2.1%.
2.1%
cost of cost of fund is 2.1%.
Similarly,
2024 2023
float. Okay. In fact, they were paid to
acquire float.
Okay. So, hope this was
they didn't have to spend any money to
raise uh uh raise float raise investment
assets.
Okay.
All right.
cost of
star you just saw it's we just estimated
is - 2.1 - 2.1
they in cost 2%. In F F523 and F524 star
health there was no cost they were paid
1.5% and 6% to acquire a float
icombardate
in the cost of float was in FI24 minus
2% FI23
okay I'll have to check whe I'll have to
double check but as an exercise okay and
write in the comment section of this
video
ICO
go digital
In 24 it was 5.5 and now 4.2%. Okay.
Cost of float should be lower than
market rate of money.
If you go to a bank and raise that same
amount, if you go to any external source
of funding, what is the rate at which
you'll raise that funding? Okay. If the
cost of flow cost of float is below uh
your cost of borrowing over time then
the insurer is raising float well below
the market rate of money and over the
long term you'll do really well. Okay.
In fact
there
all right very similar cost of float F25
okay consistently IC Lombard is doing a
great job at maintaining its cost of
float under control although although
was combined ratio
Okay.
You have to comput over time and check
if it's lower than cost of borrowing.
See, this is very important. I know I'm
stressing on it. Okay. Combined ratio
expense ratio
profitability grow. Please don't jump to
an investment.
out. Okay, now let's move forward.
Okay, the second point parameter which
again is falls under ROA which drives
ROA which impacts ROA is called float
retention period.
Buffett, Warren Buffett, what he has
said is you got to you got to calculate
what is the float size relative to
premium. Okay.
Okay. In fact,
that's also around 18,000
in float or premium size almost same
here one
premium size almost same
you would see
multi-line insurance typically float
size is almost twice
as that of their premium collection in a
given year. Okay. And again as an
exercise please compute this value for
Lombard for FI25. That's your homework.
That's your exercise comment section.
Okay? Right? See
multi-line insurers
in fact I'm telling you from my
experience multi-line insurers they are
they have a higher float size relative
to premium. Okay. or higher the float
relative to premium
you are higher retention.
You are able to retain float for a long
period of time
simple logic. So important to
retention period
ratio expense ratio.
Okay. All right.
In fact, someone asked me this question
on on YouTube key.
Do multi-line insurers do they have an
inherent advantage over moto line
insurers? Okay. And let me show you my
response as well.
All right. As I was saying, someone
asked me this question on YouTube. So
I've made a LinkedIn post on it. Okay.
So, so if you see Okay. So as for me,
the to evaluate key how multi-line mine
general shoulders are different. Okay.
One key aspect that you need to look at
is float holding period. Okay, that we
just covered. Okay, multi-line insurers
seem to be retaining float for longer.
Why do you think? First reason is
because of course multi-line insurers
are diversified. Let's say so they are
hedging their bets. If one segment
doesn't do well, okay, then they can
always focus on the they can always
focus on the uh on the other segment.
Okay. The other reason is if you read
this standard health insurers seem to be
struggling okay with frequent claim
payouts despite better claim ratios they
are they have frequent claim payouts and
hence suboptimal float retention versus
other general insurance segments to see
general insurers are multi-line general
insurers are better than moral lines
standalone health insurers doesn't mean
that okay but certainly diversified
businesses in this case like multiline
insurers Lombard go or any other medal
insurer they have this float retention
advantage. Okay. A float retention is
something which is very important in
this business as we just understood. All
right. Okay. Let's just move forward.
All right. Okay. See now see we look at
RO analysis
cost of retention because of course both
of them they contribute they drive ROA.
Okay. Next, leverage leverage per every
of how much investment assets you have
been able to accumulate over time. Okay,
so
already I've estimated investment
leverage. Okay, this is investment
leverage for all these insurers ahead of
time. Again, you do it for ICIC Lombard.
How you do it? You just divide assets by
equity. Investment assets by equity.
Okay, now in the case of insurers, high
the higher the investment leverage, the
better it is.
Okay.
Okay. Typically higher the investment
leverage the better it is. Okay. And why
do you think uh
why do you think key multi-line insurers
like ICICA go digit they have a higher
investment leverage than than let's say
the likes of star health and bupa? One
reason which in my mind is because see
insurers which have high float
retention.
Okay, they drive a higher investment
leverage. They are able to drive a
higher investment leverage. Of course,
that's which is the case with ICI and go
digital all the metal insurers. Okay.
Then you are able to earn a high
interest income. Okay. Higher interest
income. So you and that interest income
also gets added to your investment
assets over time. Okay. So investment
assets and of course you are able to
drive a higher investment leverage.
Okay.
Next factor of course is see
beyond
growth growth okay so here I have listed
a few parameters which I would not get
into in this for the in the interest of
time but of course you have to analyze
in what's the market share okay how is
the market share growing over Okay. And
then and then
what I have here n the fourth item very
important is
claim rejection here and what is the
policy ratio. Okay
very important to check fundamental
analysis when you're doing fundamental
analysis of an insurer. Okay claim
rejection
if I go to the next slide. Okay. So this
is a snapshot from a video I made on
health insurance industry. There is a
there is a general insurance key general
insurance council key website may you
get the claim rejection ratios uh of all
the insurers of all the general insurers
in India okay I have spoken about it a
whole lot when I made this video on
understanding health insurance industry
in India in fact some other videos as
well so I'll put the link in the
description if you see this is a little
dated
star health hoping that this is visible
Bstar Healthcare claim rejection ratio
was very high at 18.5%.
Okay.
And in 2023 and neup
claim rejection ratio was around what
9.1%.
High visca
rejection ratio is around 5% and
includes all the lines of insurance.
Okay.
Of course you can get a sense key. See
if you reject a lot of claims then of
course your end customers uh may not be
very happy
or see or probably the reason is because
there has been a lot of insurance
missing as well. Okay. Insurance
insurance is a push product
which probably the customer doesn't
understand and then customer requests
for a claim and
this happens a lot in health insurance.
Okay. uh probably this may I do I I
don't know but that's your judgment that
of course analyze
star may or single line insuranceers may
let's say if there is a rapid growth in
the number of agents okay then then
there may be some agent selling that may
have happened and that's why there
there's a lot of claim rejections that
have happened as well okay or or
you also have to look at policy renewal
rate as well check okay so any which
ways
any which ways to hopefully
up you now have a very good sense of
what is it that you need to analyze.
Okay, these four things that you need to
analyze in an insurance business cost of
funds retention period leverage
and then also you need to check for
certain risks like the ones that I have.
Okay, these are some of the key things
that you got to look
okay. All right.
Okay. So, yeah. Yeah. So I I'm not
getting into valuations per se of all
these insurers. Okay. But you would see
I Lombard right now is trading at a
premium. The metric that you use to
analyze insurance to analyze insurance
business PV metric price to book. Okay.
The price to book ICI is higher than all
the other general insurance companies
because I think of of the way it is
managing the way it is keeping its cost
of float you know you know at at low
levels and also because of its high
float retention period float time it's
able to retain okay and of course it's
getting the advantage of being
diversified okay to and and claim
rejection ratio be controlled here okay
so anyways hope this was helpful now
let's move on to move on to the next
key. How do we do fundamental analysis
of banks?
Hope you are finding my content
valuable. If you are an investor
interested in learning thorough
fundamental analysis and valuation or if
you're an aspiring equity research
analyst, okay, who is interested in
learning these skills to get into such
roles, then I have a program suited to
your needs. Okay? And so in my program
my uh you know I my I cover quality and
well research content. I cover diverse
industries. Okay. And the topics that I
teach in this program through live
exercise and case studies are financial
statements. I uh also teach you how to
analyze and interpret financial and
marketing ratios. It's pretty extensive.
Okay. And how to assess the forensics
and how to analyze the quality of the
management. How to read calls and annual
reports. Okay. how to analyze an
industry and how to size the market.
Okay. Uh how to assess modes in a
business, financial modeling and
valuation. And I also help you to form
and articulate your investment thesis.
So if you're someone who thinks will be
benefited by this program, then feel
free to reach out to me at my email or
reach out to me on LinkedIn. All right.
Thank you.